Brinthan Kanesalingam

 $E ext{-}mail:$ kanesalingambrinthan187@gmail.com | $Telephone\ number:$ +94 76 992 3353 | $Website \mid Google\ Scholar \mid ResearchGate \mid GitHub$

Profile and Research Focus

My research interests revolves around materials and minerals sciences, computer vision, machine learning, and computational methodologies. I am particularly interested in characterising microstructures and analysing complex electromagnetic radiation data from techniques such as imaging, fluorescence, absorption spectroscopy, and scattering. My primary focus lies in X-ray and multimodal imaging. I aim to advance understanding at the convergence of these diverse fields.

Education

Master of Science (Major Component of Research) University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka
Department of Earth Resources Engineering Sept 2022 - Present
Thesis: Enhancing coal fly ash waste-valorisation through advanced characterisation techniques

Bachelor of Science in Engineering (Honours)

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka
Department of Earth Resources Engineering
Aug 2017 - Jul 2022
Thesis: Preprocessing of coal fly ash waste for advanced material applications

Research Experience

Graduate Research Assistant Computer Science & Engineering, University of Moratuwa Data Science, Engineering and Analytics Research Hub (DataSEARCH) Feb 2024 - Present

- Engaged in research on conditional generative adversarial networks (CGANs) to enhance the resolution of microscopic images under the guidance of **Dr Uthayasanker Thayasivam**.
- Curating specialised synthetic datasets tailored for evaluating CGAN performance in superresolution tasks for microscopic images
- Designing and implementing a bespoke loss function to maintain structural integrity throughout super-resolution processes

Postgraduate ResearcherEarth Resources Engineering, University of MoratuwaMaster of Science (Major Component of Research)Sept 2022 - Dec 2023

- Investigated the characterisation of coal fly ash derivatives through X-ray micro-analysis and image processing under the guidance of **Dr Chulantha Jayawardena**, **Dr Ashane Fernando**, **Dr Shantha Amarasinghe**, and **Dr Dinesh Attygalle**.
- Contributions: Developed a novel technique for the classification of micro and cenospheres using energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy, and assessed the imperceptible structures of cenospheres.

Undergraduate Honours Thesis Earth Resources Engineering, University of Moratuwa Bachelor of Science in Engineering (Honours)

Aug 2021 - Jul 2022

- Explored the preprocessing of coal fly ash using an innovative washing method called "washing cycles". Enhanced process efficiency through the application of surface response methodology.
- Advisers: Eng. Maheshwari Wickrama, Dr Ashane Fernando, Dr Chulantha Jayawardena, and Ms Ravindi Jayasundara

Publications

 * Both $Brinthan\ K$ and $Kanesalingam\ B$ denote the same person

Unpublished Papers (Works in Review/ Preparation)

- [U4] Kanesalingam B., Fernando W.A.M., Panda S., Jayawardena C., Attygalle D., Amarasinghe D.A.S., "Strategic routes in valorising coal fly ash waste to promote circular economy". (Under Review)
- [U3] <u>Kanesalingam B.</u>, Fernando W.A.M., Jayawardena C., Attygalle D., Amarasinghe D.A.S., Panda S., Rabbani, A., "Leveraging advanced characterisation of the derivatives of pre-processed coal fly ash using deep learning and digital image processing techniques". (*Under Review*)
- [U2] Kanesalingam B., Fernando W.A.M., Jayawardena C., Attygalle D., Amarasinghe D.A.S., Panda S., Rabbani, A., "Shedding electrons on cenospheres: Advancing characterisation through X-ray micro-analysis". (Under Review)
- [U1] <u>Kanesalingam B.</u>, Fernando W.A.M., Jayawardena C., Attygalle D., Amarasinghe D.A.S., Panda S., Rabbani, A., "Micro-structural profiling of coal fly ash through Energy Dispersive X-ray Spectroscopy". (In Preparation)

Journal Articles

[J1] Kanesalingam B., Fernando W.A.M., Panda S., Jayawardena C., Attygalle D., Amarasinghe D.A.S., (2023). "Harnessing the Capabilities of Microorganisms for the Valorisation of Coal Fly Ash Waste through Biometallurgy". *Minerals*, 13(6), 724.

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers

- [C7] <u>Brinthan K.</u>, Thanujan T., Thiruchittampalam S., and Jayawardena C.L., (2023). "Subclassification of water resources with Sentinel-2 satellite imagery: Spectrabased insight". in "International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)", Pasadena, California, USA. (Invited for Journal Article)
- [C6] Brinthan K., Shivadhahini S., Senadheera U.A.G., Fernando W.A.M., Jayawardena C.L., and Jayasundara D.R.T., Wickrama M.A.D.M.G., (2023). "A Primary Pre-Processing Strategy for Coal Fly Ash to Enhance its Performance and Usability". in "World Congress on Undergraduate Research", The University of Warwick, United Kingdom.
- [C5] Jayawardena C.L., <u>Brinthan K.</u>, Gamsavi K., Samarakoon K.G.A.U., Senarathna T.M.B., (2023). "Weathered rock surface classification with unpiloted aerial vehicle imagery and machine learning". in "SLRMES Conference on Rock Mechanics for Infrastructure and Geo-Resources Development an ISRM Specialised Conference", Sri Lanka.
- [C4] <u>Brinthan K.</u>, Shivadhahini S., Senadheera U.A.G., Fernando W.A.M., Jayawardena C.L., and Jayasundara D.R.T., Wickrama M.A.D.M.G., (2022). "Experimental Investigation and

- Performance Optimisation of Washing Cycles for Pre-processing of Coal Fly Ash". in "Proceedings of ISERME 2022", University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka.
- [C3] <u>Brinthan K.</u>, Thanujan T., Thiruchittampalam S., and Jayawardena C.L., (2021). "Evaluation of Machine Learning Algorithms in Classifying Multispectral Imagery on Waterbody Extraction". in "Proceedings of ICSUSL 2021", Sabaragamuwa University of Sri Lanka, Sri Lanka.
- [C2] Thanujan T., <u>Brinthan K.</u>, Thiruchittampalam S., and Jayawardena C.L., (2021). "Evaluation of Ventilation Network through Hybrid Analytical-Numerical Approach in Underground Working Block". in "Proceedings of ISERME 2021", University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka.
- [C1] Thanujan T., <u>Brinthan K.</u>, Shivadhahini S., Subasinghe M.A.I.I.J., Vettinathan S., Dharmaratne P.G.R., Hemalal P.V.A., Chaminda S.P., and Jayawardena C.L., (2021). "A Study of Underground and Surface Mining Methods in Sri Lanka and its Suitability Assessment". in "Proceedings of ISERME 2021", University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka.

Magazine Articles

- [M2] "Rethinking coal fly ash waste for a circular tomorrow", Materials World, Institute of Materials, Minerals & Mining (IOM3), United Kingdom (Submitted for April 2024 issue as a feature article)
- [M1] "Are we going to let coal fly ash to just fly? Transforming pollution into innovation", Bolgoda Plains, University of Moratuwa (Submitted)

Research Presentations

Oral Presentations

1. "Pre-processing: A new avenue for coal fly ash circular economy", World Congress on Undergraduate Research, The University of Warwick, United Kingdom, April 2023.

Poster Presentations

- 3. "Decode subclasses of water resources with the indicator matrix", International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS) (h5-median 68), Pasadena, California, USA, July 2023.
- 2. "Demystifying the heterogeneity of coal fly ash through washing cycles", *International Summer School in Global Just Transition: Equity in Net Zero*, Newcastle University, United Kingdom, June 2023.
- 1. "Experimental investigation and performance optimisation of washing cycles for pre-processing of coal fly ash", Research Week 2023, University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka, December 2022.

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant Computer Science & Engineering, CS3111 - Introduction to Machine

University of Moratuwa Learning (Summer 2024)

Resource Person Earth Resources Engineering, ER4290 - Rock Mechanics (Fall 2023)

University of Moratuwa ER4202 - Research Project (Fall 2022

& Fall 2023)

Professional Service

Conference Organisation \mathcal{E} Editorials

• SLRMES - Conference on Rock Mechanics for Infrastructure and Geo-Resources Development - an ISRM Specialised Conference, Sri Lanka, December 2023. (Organising committee & Editorial team)

• International Symposium on Earth Resources Management and Environment 2023 (ISERME 2023), University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka, August 2023. (Editorial team)

International Conference Peer Reviews

- National Conference on Undergraduate Research 2024 (NCUR 2024), California, United States of America
- 25^{th} & 26^{th} International Conference on Paste, Thickened and Filtered Tailings (Paste 2023 2024), The University of Western Australia, Australia.
- Rocscience International Conference 2023 (RIC 2023), Toronto, Canada.
- World Congress on Undergraduate Research British Conference of Undergraduate Research 2023 (WorldCUR-BCUR 2023), The University of Warwick, United Kingdom.
- International Symposium on Earth Resources Management and Environment 2023 (ISERME 2023), University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Open Source Software Contribution

- pyDeepP2SA Advanced particle characterisation package developed using deep learning, digital image processing, and numerical computing. (Link)
- pyChemEng Rapid assessment of raw data for adsorption isotherms and kinetic models. Co-authored by Dr Ashane Fernando. (Link)

Grants and Awards

• Recipient of full scholarship from The University of Warwick to participate in the World Congress on Undergraduate Research 2023 at The University of Warwick, Coventry, United Kingdom.

- Recipient of full scholarship from UK Energy Research Centre (UKERC) to participate in the International Summer School in Global Just Transition: Equity in Net Zero at Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom. This conference has been organised and funded by nine different research consortia and institutions including: HI-ACT, Supergen Energy Networks Hub, the Energy Interdisciplinary Research Centre Cambridge, IDLES, the Faraday Institution, CREDS, UKCCSRC, UKERC, and the Energy Research Accelerator.
- Dean's List (2017 2022) honouree during Bachelor's Degree at the University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka, on three occasions.

Work Experience

Internship Trainee	May 2021 - Sept 2021	SuperMap Beijing, Chi	Co.,	Ltd.,
Trainee Irrigation Engineer	Oct 2020 - Jun 2021	Department Colombo, Si	Irrigation,	

Scientific and Professional Societies

- Member (RMS14078) Royal Microscopical Society (RMS), Oxford, England.
- Student Member (3003156) Australasian Institute of Mining & Metallurgy (AusIMM), Carlton, Australia.
- Member (20231000075) International Association for Carbon Capture (IACC).